Samuel Krafsur Papers ALBA.267
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Samuel Krafsur Papers
1937-1983
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Krafsur, Samuel Simon, 1913-1983
Krafsur, Richard P.
ALBA.267
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Samuel ("Bill") Krafsur (1913-1983) volunteered to fight in the Spanish Civil War with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. He was wounded in Spain in May and returned to the U.S. in July 1937. In the spring of 1938 he was in New York, serving as an editorial staff member of The Volunteer for Liberty, published by the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. The collection includes correspondence, medical records, identity cards, other printed ephemera, and clippings that document Krafsur's service and other aspects of the Spanish Civil War. There are also a small number of items relating to Krafsur's subsequent career in journalism.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Samuel Krafsur File, ALBA Vertical Files Other ALBA collections.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 1 series: I: General Files, 1937-1983.
Missing Title
Series I: General Files, 1937-1983.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes correspondence, documents, identity cards, ephemera, and clippings that document Samuel Krafsur's service in and other apsects of the Spanish Civil War. There are also a small number of items relating to his subsequent career in journalism.
Series I: General Files, 1937-1983, contains one letter to Samuel Krafsur from the Spanish Prisoners Revue; medical certificates; press passes; flyers/handbills for theater and other events during the Civil War; Krafsur's International Brigades identity card; membership cards for Socorro Rojo International, the Aerican Newspaper Guild and the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; and his U.S. Passport. There are also a number of clippings regarding Abraham Lincoln Brigade veterans and an obituary.
Provenance
The collection was donated to the ALBA archives at the Tamiment Library, NYU in August 2008, by Samuel Krafsur's son, Richard Krafsur.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Separated Materials
Two photographs of Krafsur (one circa 1950, one circa 1960) were temporarily moved to ALBA PHOTOS 164 (Box 6) and will eventually be integrated into ALBA PHOTOS 15.
Historical/Biographical Note
Samuel Simon ("Bill") Krafsur was born January 10, 1913 in Boston, Massachusetts. He attended Northeastern University for a year, and is alleged to have joined the Communist Party in the 1930s. He volunteered to fight in Spain and sailed on the SS Paris in January 16, 1937, arriving at Le Havre, France on January 23rd. He joined the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain, was reported as wounded in May 1937 and left Spain through Barcelona in July 1937. In the spring of 1938, he was in New York, serving as an editorial staff member of The Volunteer for Liberty, a publication of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. He also worked a secretary to the novelist (and his one-time brother-in-law), Elliot Paul, author of Life and Death of a Spanish Town.
Krafsur worked for TASS, the Soviet news agency, in New York and in Washington, DC covering Capitol Hill and the White House, from 1941 to 1949. In the 1950s, he operated Rogers Toy Store in Bethsda, MD, and sold real estate in the DC area. In 1956 he told the Senate Internal Security Subcommittee that he was not then, and had not been during his employment at TASS, a member of the Communist Party. (The recent release of material from the Venona Files brought allegations that he was an agent of Soviet Intelligence during this period.) He declined to answer questions relating to the period before 1940. Krafsur worked for the British news agency Reuters from 1959 to 1978, first as Washington office manager, then, from 1968, as a correspondent covering financial and commodity news. He lived, in retirement, in St. Petersburg, FL, and died while visiting relatives in Memphis, TN in June 1983. An obituary in Reuters World referred to his "vast knowledge of the Washington scene" and described him as "a delightful man and an excellent journalist."
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Identity cards.; Printed ephemera.; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Krafsur, Samuel Simon, 1913-1983; Krafsur, Richard P.
- Series I: General Files, 1937-1983.
  - American Newspaper Guild, 1937, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clipping (unidentified) re: Aid to Wounded Massachisetts Volunteers, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, [1968],1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Peter Frye and Irving Fajans to SK (1 letter, re: Spanish Prisoners Revue), Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Flyers: Film Screening, "La Mujer X" (Alcala, Teatro-Salon Cervantes; PS/UGT); "Gran Baile" (Juventudas Socialistas Unificadas); "Fiesta de Liberacion del Pueblo Americano" (4th of July, Albacete), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Identity Card (Carnet Militaire), Membership Cards, Safe Conduct Pass, Handwritten Pass(?), and U.S. Passport, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Marlow, Inver (aka John Scott): Obituary, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Medical Documents re: SK (unfit for service at the front, etc.), Jun 8, 1937; Jul 6, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Obituary: Reuters World, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Press Passes, 1949-1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)